If men are optimized, what your
experience concerning their total and
free tea levels on which they feel good
with all symptoms gone. So this is
something that differs for everybody. So
as I go through that process where we're
evaluating people every 3 months
eventually, yes, we do get to a point
where your body composition is ideal for
longevity. Okay, which what is that?
It's usually for men a percent body fat
15 to 20%. It's higher if they have
heart disease. If they're totally
healthy, maybe like 12 to 15%. There's
some evidence that's the best. Okay. Um,
and then skeletal muscle we want to be
good. You know, there's no exact target.
We want to be definitely above normal,
not low, right? Okay. So, and that's
going to differ um for everybody based
on their, you know, height, weight,
genetics, things like that. So, what do
I do when all that body composition
stuff is perfect? Well, what we try to
target is a testosterone trough level of
around a thousand. We do not use free
testosterone targets. Why? Because the
very limited long-term epidemiology is
all using total testosterone levels, not
free testosterone levels. And free
testosterone levels are very useful for
people who are not on testosterone. like
determining
for example when you put someone on TRT
very early their change in free
testosterone is more predictive of of of
um better symptomatic improvement than
their total testosterone level. Okay, so
that is true but that's on a short time
scale and then the other studies are
looking at free testosterone and people
who aren't diagnosed. So people who have
normal total testosterone below free
testosterone, those patients can still
benefit from TRT. So it's important to
know that when you've been on TRT for
several years, your free testosterone I
don't think is nearly as relevant.
At this current moment with the current
evidence and studies that we have right
now. So, someone who's been on
testosterone for three years, who I've
helped get from 40% body fat down to
maybe like 18 20%. Okay. I'm not as
worried about what their trough
testosterone level is as what their
total testosterone level is. And the
general target is about around a
thousand around a thousand.
>> Now, the important thing for to say
though is that is not possible in most
men. it's not possible to maintain
adequate body composition and um while
also of course we want to limit side
effects like we don't want you know if
people are having side effects we don't
push their dose higher like right away
so assuming all that stuff is okay um
some men have to tolerate higher levels
just to maintain their body composition
and I found that what happens is I'll
get a guy okay we've reached your body
composition goals you're on a low dose
of a GOP1 or maybe off the simaglletide
or trapatide completely
um but your total is like 1,400 let's
say let's decrease the dose by 5 to 10%
then 3 months later everything again all
your labs body composition now when I do
that the first time they may come back
and their levels 1250 or something but
their body composition stayed good and
It feels good. They don't feel any
worse. Okay, let's try another five or
10%.
>> Okay, 3 months later, everything is
still good. They feel pretty good. And
now we're maybe at 1,100.
I have found with a lot of experience,
if I try to do a third 10% reduction,
more than 50% of the time, I'm going to
cause problems. Their body composition
is going to go the other way. They're
going to start feeling not as good. I'm
going to cause issues. So, I just don't
usually do it after two. Okay. Um, and
patients that are really concerned about
wanting to get to a thousand, which vast
majority aren't. Um, but in ones who
are, okay, then yeah, we'll cut again.
The problem is once you once long term,
once you go down and you start to feel
worse and your body composition starts
to worsen,
a lot of times if I go back to your old
dose, that that won't even fully work.
And I don't know if that's
a mental effect or a a drug effect. It's
probably a combination of both. So yes,
I try to target a total level of around
a thousand. That's a trough level. So
that'd be the day that you inject before
you inject. So let's say you're
injecting every four days. Okay? It'd be
on the fourth day at the time you'd
inject before you inject. That's what we
look for. And like I and based on how
frequently some people inject it's also
not possible even to get to that level.
But you know everybody is different and
um a lot of it is also a risk tolerance
thing. There are some guys in their 60s
and I'm like you know your total
testosterone level is 1300. We don't
know that's safe. It could shorten your
life. Maybe it's associated heart attack
strokes 5 10 years in the future. I
don't give a I feel good. Just
leave everything alone. Please, for the
love, just please leave everything
alone.
That's different than a guy who's 32,
okay, who has hopefully many, many
decades in front of him. We want to be
more cautious, right? Because we don't
technically have super long-term safety
studies on TRT, the way most people
administer TRT.
>> One remark on your uh 1,000 total
testosterone in the chat box. Uh, what
about people with high SHBG? Uh, Simon
says, "I got on TRT when my total
testosterone was 1,200."
>> Like he started TRT when his total
testosterone was,200.
>> That's what he says. But he says uh when
people have a very high SHBG, you can
the PT will be low.
>> Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. So
when I say t when I say a everybody
that's why I said everybody's different
you know um somebody with there are
certain people with congenally very high
SHPG what should happen is when they get
androgens it should lower their SHPG 90%
of the time it does especially with like
synthetic well I guess testosterone is a
synthetic androgen technically but
non-testosterone androgens
including many orals will usually very
potently lower your SHG that doesn't
happened to everybody and so yeah pat
some patients have to have doses that
are higher because their SHBG is higher
and that's the way it is and um I'm not
sure if there was a question in what he
said but yeah it's not like a strict
thing like I was explaining it's an in
very highly individualistic thing
>> okay I have a a physician patient right
now for example his total testosterone
level is higher than a thousand I'll
just put it to you like that. His SHBG
is very high. He's like, "It is what it
is. If you lower the dose, I feel
terrible. So, I guess we got to stay at
this one." His dose is still would be
considered a TRT dose, but it's higher
than the majority of patients.
>> But that's an example of a doctor with,
>> you know, so yeah, everybody's uh has to
be treated differently. For me,
>> unlike a lot of TRT clinics, I'm not
like, how do you feel? Do you feel
better today than the day you came in
when we had this dose? I care a lot more
about body composition. I do care about
people's sex drive, libido, especially
if those things are getting worse. But
um and work related performance. I I ask
and I care about all those things, side
effects, blood pressure, but body
composition to me is where all the a lot
of the money is at because that's what's
really going to move the needle for
somebody. Okay. giving somebody these
lower doses of testosterone for years
and oh maybe I feel a little bit better
but their body composition doesn't
change you're not doing much for them
medically I mean that's like I told you
I had that guy he started testosterone
body fat 35% now it's 37 now maybe it
would have been much higher had he not
been on testosterone almost guaranteed
it would have
>> but you ought to be a little bit more
aggressive than that we live in an
environment that poisons us constantly
um in many many ways. This is going to
be what my second book is about um is
about you know environmental endocrine
disrupting chemicals. The biggest one is
the our light environment that we live
in uh causes circadian rhythm
disruption. So it's unavoidable uh for
men in our society to avoid things that
tend to
not only lower their testosterone levels
but promote metabolic disease in
general. And you can see that just in
the um you know just in the statistics
right we used to have in this country a
childhood obesity rate of less than 1%.
Now it's about 20%.
Okay. Um 5% of adults in the US had high
blood pressure. Now it's like 50%. 120
million people. Okay. And then if you
look at like med just diabetes used to
be 1% now it's like close to 15%. And
40% of people have what's called
pre-diabetes. So in the span of a
hundred years our society has gotten
significantly sicker than what we were.
>> Yeah.
>> Do we have worse medical care today than
we did 100 years ago? No. We have all
this fancy technology. We have all these
drugs. We have a variety of novel weight
loss drugs and things like that. Um, but
the problem has slowly, not even slowly,
the problem has pretty rapidly gotten
much, much worse. And it's the
environmental issues causing or
promoting the metabolic syndrome and
then the testosterone issue is
downstream of all the metabolic issues.
The good thing is it looks like from
many recent studies that testosterone
can help reverse a lot of the metabolic
dysfunction that men are living under
and pretty safely but with a lot of
long-term unknowns.